<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Information for Alexander Dunbar of Westfield heretable sheriff of Elgin and Forres. Against the Laird of Grant.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B09270</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">80922869</idno>
  <idno type="VID">191893</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240871811</idno>
  
            <idno type="OCLC"> 80922869</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing I163BA</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R188856</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">80922869</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B09270)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 191893)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; 1641-1700 ; 2894:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Information for Alexander Dunbar of Westfield heretable sheriff of Elgin and Forres. Against the Laird of Grant.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>9 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard Law School Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Dunbar, Alexander.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Sheriffs --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Elginshire (Scotland) --  Politics and government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Forres (Scotland) --  Politics and government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:191893:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:191893:1"/>
            <head>
               <hi>INFORMATION</hi> For <hi>Alexander Dunbar</hi> of <hi>Westfield</hi> heretable Sheriff of <hi>Elgin</hi> and <hi>Forres.</hi> Against The Laird of <hi>Grant.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Laird of <hi>Grant</hi> having lately obtained from his Majesty a Signature erecting his Lands in a Regality, and a part of his Lands lying local<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly within the Shire of <hi>Elgin,</hi> when this Signature was presented to be past the Exchequer, <hi>Dunbar</hi> of <hi>Westfield</hi> heretable Sheriff of the said Shire opposed and protested against it, as hurtful and prejudicial to his heretable Sheriff-ship, and <hi>Grant</hi> having now past Infeftment of the said Signature, the Sheriff for vindicating of his heretable Office, and the bounds thereof from such a manifest Incroachment, hath raised a Reduction and Declarator to hear and see it found and declared, that <hi>Grants</hi> Signature of a Regality, cannot be extended to, nor comprehend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> of the Land<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>ging to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in prejudice of the said Sheriffs heretable Office, but the samen ought in so far to be declared and reduced.</p>
            <p>This Action being called in the Inner house, it was alledged, that the Laird of <hi>Grant</hi> had also raised a Reduction and Declarator against the Sheriff for taken away of his heretable Office of Sheriff-ship, but the Production not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing satisfied by the Sheriff, in so far as was requisit for debating of <hi>Grants</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction and Declarator, and on the other hand, the Sheriffs Reduction, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim against <hi>Grant</hi> being ready to be debated, the Sheriff insisted in his Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and some little Qustion having been moved about his Title, as if his Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sin on his Retour as Heir to his Father were not sufficient; The Lords allowed him to produce farder <hi>eum processu,</hi> which is also done, the Sheriffs heretable Sheriffship being indeed uncontestable, and founded in a clear Progress of more than a hundreth Years with an interrupted Possession.</p>
            <p>It was therefore alleadged for the Sheriff, that the Ground and Reason of his Reduction and Declarator, was in it self so clear and so clearly founded in one of the first Maxims of Law, viz. <hi>quod meum est sine facto meo aufferri non potest,</hi> or that no mans property can be taken from him without his own consent, or the force of Law which is equivalent, that it was not capable ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of farder Probation or Illustration; But <hi>ita est</hi> that the foresaid heretable Office within the whole bounds teereof is the Sheriffs undoubted Right and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:191893:2"/> Property, and therefore cannot be taken away or diminished by the Laird of <hi>Grant</hi> either in whole or in part, without the Sheriffs own consent, or the deed of Law which is equivalent.</p>
            <p>To this there were several Answers and Exceptions made by the Laird of <hi>Grant,</hi> which for shuning of Repetition shall be notised and taken off by the Sheriff in order as they were proponed, and are now resumed. 1. It was An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered for <hi>Grant,</hi> that there was a Distinction to be made betwixt an Office tho' heretable, and other Rights of Property, in as far as an Office was in effect but only a Power and Commission flowing from the King, who still retained the Soveraign Power, and by vertue thereof might erect other Offices, as that of Regality within the bounds of any Shire, albeit it should be found restri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive or prejudicial to the heretable Office of Sheriff-ship, whereas other Rights of Property as of Lands and Tenements were full and absolute, and by the Law secured from all Diminutions and Incroachments; And farder, that a bare Office was not to be judged <hi>in patrimonio,</hi> and could never hinder the King to erect Regalities which were Praedial and Feudal Jurisdictions, which the King in all time might give with the Feu of the Lands at his pleasure.</p>
            <p>To which it was replyed for the Sheriff, that this Answer and Distinction was neither founded in Law nor Reason, but in effect did militat as well against the Defenders Regality, as the Sheriffs Sheriff-ship; The Defenders Procura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors in proponing this Allegiance, acting clearly <hi>Sampsons</hi> Part, who to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy the <hi>Philistines,</hi> pulled down the House, and involved himself in the same Ruines; It being evident that if heretable Offices cannot be reckoned Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty, but are still subject to be limited or restricted by the Kings Soveraign Power, the same may happen as well to an heretable Regality, as an here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Sheriff-ship, nor doth it signifie any thing, that the Office of Regality is praedial or Feudal, and annexed to Lands, because the Question here is, not concerning the nature of Regalities, but precisely this, whether the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Office of Sheriff-ship being lawfully constitute, can be diminished by the erecting of a Regality within the same bounds, seing whether the Regality be annexed to Lands or not, it is not material to this Question whereof the precise point is, whether a prior Right of the Office of Sheriff ship can be taken from the Sheriff without his own Deed or Law, by erecting another Office within the same bounds, manifestly privative of the Sheriff-ship, whether that other Office be called a Regality or not, or whether this Office of Rega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity be annexed to Lands or not? And without Controversie, if the King should grant a Feu of certain Lands within a Shire, with an Office of Bailliary, or of any other Designation, but still privative of the Sheriffs Jurisdiction, the heretable Sheriff might still reclaim, notwithstanding of its being annexed to Lands, which plainly makes no material difference in this case.</p>
            <p>But 2. The Defenders material Error is, that he would have a heretable Office to be no Property nor Right, and in effect it cannot well be said what he would make it, or how he would distinguish it from any precarious Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission, but setting aside these dark Notions, it is granted that a heretable Office is neither Lands nor Tenements, but <hi>quid incorporium,</hi> is it therefore not capable of Right or Property, when it is certain it hath all Marks, Characters and Uses of any other Right, in so far as it may be transmitted to Heirs, it may be Gifted or Sold, or Apprysed, and even as to the Soveraign Power whence it flows, it is so far a Right of Property, that the King hath himself bought back heretable Sheriff-ship by a considerable Price, and the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:191893:2"/> Defender contends that they are still redeemable, seing therefore that a here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Office is a mans Property as well as a heretable Right of Land, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders distinction is wholy groundless, and farder it is certain that an here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Office hath not only Emoluments and Perquisits, which even the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender cannot deny to be <hi>in patrimonio,</hi> but also that the heretable Office it self, seing it may be Bought and Sold is patrimonial.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Absurdity and Impertinency of the foresaid distinction as to the case in hand, is yet more manifest; If it shall be inquired, whether the King may on the ground thereof erect another Sheriff-ship within a Sheriff-ship, or if he may dismember a Shireff-ship, and no doubt both will be denyed; If then he may not erect another Shireff-ship within the Bounds of an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retable Sheriff-ship, or dismember a Sheriff-ship by making two of one even albeit he should grant this new Erection with an annexation to Lands, <hi>multo minus</hi> may he erect a Regality, because a Reg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lity in effect is as privative of the Sheriff-ship, as if it were another Shire: And it is a mistake, as if the priviledge of Regality were only to repledge from the Sheriff, and to have some Casualities of Escheat, and the like which the Sheriff hath not, when in effect the Bounds of the Regality are so distinct from the Shireff ship that they are plainly <hi>alterum territorum,</hi> and a Sheriff by the Act of Parliament, in the Pursuit of a Man-slayer, or Robber, is to behave to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a neigbouring Lord of Regality, as toward a neighbouring Sheriff. It is true, that as the Lord of Regality, hath some powers of Jurisdiction as well as Casualities beyond the Sheriff, so the Sheriff hath power in some Cases, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven within the Regality; as to fortifie his Court with Suits out of the Regality, when they are wanting out of the Shire: And to raise the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the Regality with the rest of the <hi>poss-comitatus,</hi> but it is as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that these are only measures of Policy and Government, and making no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the present question, which is precisely this, whether an Heretable Sheriff-ship can be diminished or incroached upon by Erecting of a Regality, which is clearly privative, and if by the same Rule, the whole Sheriff-ship may not be exhausted, by erecting the like Regalities over the whole Shire, which is plainly the same, as if an old Heretable Sheriff-ship were Dismem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred in so many New Sheriff-ships, as should leave the old Sheriff nothing but the Name, which were most absurd: But seing the Heretable Office of Sheriff is truly the Sheriffs Property, for which he payes a distinct <hi>Redendo,</hi> wherein he makes his Equie every year, and that it hath all the marks of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty, and is in <hi>patrimonio</hi> as said is. It is certain that in Law, and by the Kings real Intention which is never by any Gift to take away another Mans Right, it can no more be diminished in part, or destroyed in the whole, for both are the same thing, by new Regalities, than by new Bailliaries, Sheriff-ships, or other exclusive Jurisdictions, for names are but names and signifie no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
            <p>But here it was farder urged for the pursuer, that in the late Times, <hi>viz.</hi> In the year 1681. there was an Act made for the Kings cumulative Jurisdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, which all men know was purposely designed, not as the Defender alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to have some Laws more sharply execute, but really to diminish some He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retable Jurisdiction, and yet this Law by an express Act of Parliament in the year 1690: was abrogat, if then the granting of cumulative Jurisdictions, in prejudice of Heretable Rights, was judged a Grievance, and abrogat, how much more the granting of private Jurisdictions, which are evidently
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:191893:3"/> ly a far greater Nonsense. And farder it is to be remembred, that even when the Parliament 1693. did make the Act for a Commission of Justiciary in the High-lands, they would not incroach upon the Heretable Justicia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Earl of <hi>Argle</hi> and others, without their own consent, and if any Person having Lands within the Justiciary of <hi>Argyle,</hi> or of <hi>Caithness, &amp;c.</hi> Should obtain a Regality to be Erected, it would certainly be reprobat: How can it then be questioned, but that an Heretable Sheriff may Defend his Right in like manner.</p>
            <p>As to what the Defender here answered, that the Act anent Cumulative Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdictions, was made for a warrant to give Commissions to Officers to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the then Laws, as Sheriffs in that Part, in place of the ordinary Sheriffs. And therefore, and for no other Reason abrogat, it was reasonably replyed, that as to that excess and abuse of the Cumulative Jurisdiction, it was Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by the Claim of Right, but the Estates and the Parliament went yet farder, and found, That the very power of Erecting new Jurisdictions <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulativè,</hi> within the Bounds of Old Jurisdictions, was a Grievance, and therefore did abrogat it, which concludes <hi>a fortiori,</hi> that the Erecting of new privative Jurisdictions within the same Bounds, are <hi>multo magis</hi> to be repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, and in effect are so contrary to the fundamental Rule of Right, that there is no need of a positive Constitution to discharge them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It was alledged for the Defender, that the Custom hath now been for many years, that the King hath granted several Regalities within the Bounds of Heretable Sheriff-ships, and this hath been generally acquiesced to, nor hath it hitherto been disproven in Judgement, so that the old Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Ja. 2. Discharging the Erecting of New Regalities: without the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance of Parliament, is gone in desuetude, and the contrary Custom hath taken place.</p>
            <p>To which it was replyed, for the Pursuer, that this Alledgeance of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stom, is most groundless and frivolous, seing that any Custom that can be condescended on, is meerly <hi>consuetudo facti,</hi> which hath no binding power, or Warrand in it. Because 1. It is but resent, and none of the late Erecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Regalities, hath yet so much as attained to prescription, much less can a binding Custom be thence inferred. 2. Because this Custom is not general, or universal, which is another Charecter of a binding Custom. 3. Because no Custom contrary to Law, or private Right, can never be binding, but this Custom of Regalities is contrary to Law, <hi>viz.</hi> The foresaid express Act of Parliament, and albeit it be granted, that the said Act of Parliament is not in that fresh observance, to cry down, and reduce all contrair Reg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lities, yet it will not be doubted, but that the Act of Parliament is still of that conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, as to hinder any Custom to prescribe against it, in prejudice of any mans private Right; And it is very observable, that the Act of Parliamenr hath not only since been made a perpetual Article of our Kings Revocations, who expresly revoke all Regalities, as contrary to Law, but hath also still had the force, that to this day it cannot be condescended on, that ever there was such a Decision establishing a Regality, by way of Regality, against any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans Right, and that the foresaid Custom of Regality is contrary to privat Right cannot be denyed, even by the Defenders, since it no dobut, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minishes the Right of the Heretable Sheriffs, where ever it happens: And therefore can never be judged a binding Custom. And further, it is certain, that if all <hi>Scotland</hi> should by never so long ane acquiescence, much more,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:191893:3"/> when the acquiescence is not yet the length of Prescription, suffer their privat Rights to be diminished, yet it would never prove a Custom to bind any single man, who had stood out to depart from his Right, it being in this case abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely necessary, that Customs prejudicial in this sort should be established by a tract of Decisions, to give them the force of a binding Law, nor doth this in the least militat against the Kings power and gift, who certainly never gives any thing to the prejudice of private Rights, but if any Gift of that kind happen to be Impetrat, it is only <hi>periculo impetrantis,</hi> but in so far as it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bords from the intention of the Kings Justice and Goodness; it is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood as the deed of the Impetrator, rather than of His Majesty. But 4. The late Gifts of Regalities have for the most part been reclaimed against by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tests taken in Exchequer, whereof many instances can be given, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly the Pursuer produces the Protest, both taken and admitted in Exchequer, against the Regality of <hi>Athol</hi> by the Earls of <hi>Argile</hi> and <hi>Breadalbin,</hi> and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral others: By all which it is evident, that the alledged custom of granting Regalities, is only <hi>consuetudo facti,</hi> and no binding Custom to found any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence in prejudice of the Pursuer. And farder, if it were worth the inquiry, it would be found that the acquiescing of persons concerned to the foresaid new Erections, hath proceeded from private Motives and Bargains, but it is enough for the Pursuer, that this pretended Custom cannot be alledged to be a binding Custom, and that he for himself is very far from acquiescing to it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It was alledged for the Defender, that the King hath always granted, and every day grants new Baronies within Heretable Sheriff-ships, and the same neither has, nor can be questioned. If then he grant Baronies, why not Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galities? Seing <hi>magis &amp; minus non variant speciem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which it was Replyed, 1. That the Maxim <hi>majus &amp; minus non variant speciem,</hi> was never admitted either in Morals, Politicks, or Questions of Law. 2. That the difference betwixt Baronies and Regalities is vast, in as far as it is certain, that except a small Right of Pretention, the Baron hath nothing that in the least prejudges the Sheriff; and the same Right of Pretention is in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect rather an ease than prejudice to the Sheriff; whereas a Regality is quite privative of the Sheriffs Jurisdiction, diminishes his <hi>Territorium,</hi> and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently both his Jurisdiction and <hi>Imperium,</hi> and erects a new Jurisdiction, as distinct from, and Collateral with him, as a new Sheriff-ship, and all within the Sheriff-bounds, whereby in effect by a few more Regalities, the Sheriff-Shire may be quite evacuat. But 3. Baronies as they are no ways privative of the Sheriffs Jurisdiction, so they are therewith plainly co-ordinat and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinat thereto within the same bounds, and perpetually owned as such by all our Acts of Parliament; so that the Law arising from these Acts, doth esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish Baronies; whereas on the other hand the Acts of Parliament Reprobat Regalities, unless granted in Parliament, and all our Kings have constantly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocked them, which is a most manifest disparity. And whereas it was alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Defender, that Regalities and Baronies were in this equal, because the power of Regalities was as well defined by Law, as the power of Baronies, which is all the Argument imports. It was Replyed, that the Argument is not taken from the abstract power of Baronies, but the disparity alledged by the Pursuer lyes in this, that the very co-ordination &amp; subordination of Baronies within Shires, appears to be constantly supposed and ratified by Acts of Parliament, which can no ways be said of Regalities, which not only excludes the Sheriffs power, but are expresly condemned by several Acts of Parliament.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:191893:4"/>
            <p>But 4. The manifest disparity betwixt Baronies and Regalities, in order to Sheriff-ships, lyes in this; that the Sheriff is in effect a Superior Officer to the Baron: so that the making of an Heretable Sheriff doth no more hinder the making of a Baron, than the making of any other Superior Officer hinders the making of an Inferior, which as to Regalities is quite contrary, in as much as a Regality is plainly exclusive and privative of the Sheriffs power, and so cuts off his Territory: That if all the Shire were erected in Regalities, the Sheriff and his Heretable Office should become a Cypher, and he obliged to pay a <hi>Reddendo</hi> for just nothing, which can never be so much as thought of Baronies. But to clear this point to full satisfaction, it is to be remembred, that Baronies are certainly the first and most ancient Feudal Dignities and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdictions that are known: Likeas the Barons make the most considerable State in the Kingdom; and it is amongst the chief of His Majesties Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, that he creats Barons at his pleasure; next that Sheriffs were superin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to Barons, for the better Government and Policy of the Kingdom, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing appointed to their respective Shires and Provinces, including several Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and as a Superior Officer over the Barons; and therefore the Sheriff is by our old Lawyers most fitly called and compared to the <hi>Praeses Provinciae</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Romans,</hi> and the Barons are obliged to attend as Suiters in his Courts, and he may sit or appoint persons to sit with the Barons in their Courts: And farder,, of old there lay an Appeal from the Baron to the Sheriff: Whence it follows, 3. That as this superinducing of Sheriffs did dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish nothing of the Barons Rights, so the Office of Sheriff being Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior, doth still imply a power to the King, to Creat Inferior Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons as formerly; and being thus co-ordinat with, and subordinat to the Sheriff within the same Bounds, and constantly approven for such by our Acts of Parliament, it is scarce possible to imagine how the making of an Heretable Sheriff should hinder the after-creating of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronies, since it plainly here includes that power as naturally reserved. But 4. As to Regalities all things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> contrary, For first. It may well be believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that their Original was a Church Incroachment upon the Crown, and that it was in effect the Prelats of the Church who alway pretending to Exempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, rested not till they got their Prelacies erected in Regalities. 2. That it is very likely that some of the greater Barons were incouraged by their example, and got their Lands erected in Regalities, when probably there were few He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retable Sheriff-ships. But 3. This is certain that there is no mention of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galities in our old Law, until the Reign of <hi>Robert</hi> the Second, so it is manifest that the Abuse of Regalities was soon noticed, <hi>viz.</hi> In the Reign of King <hi>James</hi> the Second, and no doubt it was both for their Incroachments upon the Crown, and their Incroachments upon Sheriffs and other ordinary Jurisdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, that by the Act of <hi>Pael. Ja.</hi> 2. <hi>par.</hi> 11. 43. <hi>cap.</hi> they were discharged to be granted without deliverance of the Parliament: Likeas ever since they have made an Article in our Kings Revocations, by all which it is evident, that Baronies are co-ordinat and connatural to Sheriff-ships, whereas Regalities are privative, and effect destructive of them, so that to argue from the instance of Baronies, which is most consistent with a Sheriff-ship to that of Regalities, which is utterly inconsistent, is ill and absurd <hi>Logick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Defender did here take notice, that Heretable Officers are likeways discharged in the very next Law to that discharging Regalities, but that is nothing to the present purpose, seing the Pursuer is not craving that the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders Regality may be simply discharged, but only contends that so long
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:191893:4"/> as heretable Offices and Regalities are both allowed, the Defenders Regality ought and should be restricted, and declared not to extend to the Pursuers prejudice.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Defender alledged, that it was incontraverted, that Stewartries might be Erected even where there are Heretable Sheriffs, but to that it was shortly and plainly Replyed, but there was no Parity betwixt Stewartries and Regalities, in as much as Stewartries are only Erected in, and over the Kings Property, and it cannot be doubted that the granting of a Heretable Sheriff-Ship does naturally imply that Exception. <hi>viz.</hi> That the King may exempt his own Property from the Sheriffs Power, unless that any man can think, that the King himself and his Court residing as they may do with in the Kings Property, should yet be subject to the Sheriffs Jurisdiction, which were ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surd, but as to Regalities there is no such ground for their Erection, but they are in effect discharged by Law as Invasions both of the King and Sheriffs Rights.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It was alledged for the Defender, that the King might erect Burghs Royal within heretable Sheriff ships, and therefore may also erect Regalities; To which it was Replyed. 1. That a Burgh-Royal as to the points of Juris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction differs little or nothing from the power of a Barony, and therefore is only to co ordinat and not at all exclusive of the Sheriff. 2. That the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguishing Priviledges of a Burgh-Royal, are the Liberties of Trade and the Immunities thereto pertaining, which are nothing prejudicial to the Sheriff-ship. 3. That if a Burgh royal came to be Erected with the Power of Sheriff-ship, as several Burghs have it, no doubt a heretable Sheriff would have both Law and Reason to oppose it and it could not in Law be granted to his prejudice. And 4. The erecting of Burghs-royal, which makes the Third State of the Kingdom, is peculiar to his Majesties Prerogative, which must still be understood to be excepted, and untouched in the Grant of any Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Sheriff ship; But as to Regalities they only derogat from the Kings pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Casualities, &amp; are inconsistant with and privative of the Sheriff, Jurisdic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and therefore are by Law discharged, and every heretable Sheriff is most clearly founded in the surest Rules of Law and Right to oppose them in so far as they encroach upon, or are prjudicial to his Right and Heretable Office.</p>
            <p n="6">6. It was farder moved by the Defender, that the Pursuer might declare whether he did insist for reducing of his Regality <hi>simpliciter</hi> as encroaching upon, and prejudicial to his Right of heretable Sheriff-ship, or if he only cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the said Regalitie te be reduced, as to these Powers and Jurisdictions, wherein it did prejudge the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ursuers foresaid heretable Office, for seing that a Regality did include a Jurisdiction, <hi>viz.</hi> as to the Power of Life and Death, and Crimes capital greater than was competent to the Sheriff, and did also give Right to the Escheats and other Casualities, which the Sheriff had no Right to it was more reasonable that the Pursuer should only quarrel the Defenders Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gality as to these points wherein it concurred with and diminished the Sheriffs Right, but not at all as to these other Powers and Casualities to which the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riff could not pretend.</p>
            <p>To which it was Replyed for the Pursuer, that he insisted in the Conclusion of his Declarator as lybelled, <hi>viz.</hi> to hear and see it declared, that the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders Regality could not be extended to any part of the bounds of the Shire nor was it he to divide and distinguish the foresaid Right of Regality which he
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:191893:5"/> conceived to be <hi>jus individuum,</hi> and to be so granted by then Defenders signa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. 2. If the Defender should offer to divide and distingush his Regality in manner foresaid, <hi>viz.</hi> that it should only subsist within the bounds of the Shire as to these Powers and Casualities that did not at all pertain to the Office of Sheriff-ship, this was not only to set up a new Office, but a manifest Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pingement upon the Act of Parliament discharging the Kings Casualities to be given away in great as of a Shire or Countrey side; For albeit something might be pleaded for the generality of a Right to Escheats when only given as a consequent of the Jurisdiction of Regality, yet to pretend that the Right to the Escheats in general should subsist where the power of Jurisdiction was substracted, was plainly contrair to the foresaid Act of Parliament, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Pursuer insisted to have the Defenders Regality in so far as it incroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the bounds of the Shire <hi>simpliciter</hi> reduced, and that without any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinction, since the Defenders Gut contained none, and was in so far privative and exclusive of the Pursuers Heretable Office, which neither the nature of his Right nor Law did allow.</p>
            <p>The Pursuers might farder represent to the Lords, the particular inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencies of extending this <hi>Highland</hi> Regality as in effect it was to the bounds of the <hi>Lowlands,</hi> but seing the Pursuer was sufficiently founded in the point of Right in general, <hi>viz.</hi> that his Property and Right of heretable Sheriff could not be taken from him either in whole or in part, without his own deed or the force of a Law, and that the extending of this Regality within the Bounds of the Shire was realy in so far privative and exclusive of the Sheriffs heretable Office, that therefore in so far it ought to be reduced.</p>
            <p>The Pursuer doth farder, with all Submission offer to the Lords considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, That albeit it may be yeilded, That the giving of Regalities in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, have not these many years been quarrelled upon the foresaid Act of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, as granted without deliverance of Parliament, yet that may be as true upon the other hand, that hitherto no Decision of the Lords can be conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scended on positively, sustaining a Gift of Regality, without deliverance of Parliament, contrairy to the said Act, much less sustaining the same in a direct Opposition to, and Competition with another Heretable Office, standing unreduced.</p>
            <p>The Defender did also Alleadge, That his Regality was Ratified in Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, But 1. a Ratification in Course, and which passes <hi>salvo jure,</hi> is not at all the Deliverance of Parliament requisit by the foresaid Act, to make a Gift of Regality lawful. And 2. The Pursuer did protest against the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said Ratification in Parliament, as he had protested against the Gift, when it past the Exchequer, whereby it was certain, that the Pursuer did preserve his Right unprejudged by the foresaid Ratification, as the Act <hi>salvo jure</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly statute.</p>
            <p>By all which, it is evident, That the Defenders Right of Regality cannot subsist within the bounds of the Shire, to the manifest hurt of the Pursuers Heretable Office of Sheriff-ship and that the Pursueris founded both in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Right, and likewayes, on the foresaid Acts of Parliament, That the foresaid Heretable Right of Sheriff-ship, which is his Property, cannot be taken from him without his own Deed, or the force of Law, which is equival<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent by the Defenders inconsistant privative and exclusive Regality.</p>
            <p>The Defender, since the Debate, and which he may possibly insert in his Information, alleadges, out of <hi>Hopes</hi> Collection, That there was an Act of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:191893:5"/> Parliament in K. <hi>James</hi> the fourth's time, impowering the King to Unite, Disjoyne, and Erect Sheriff-ships, as he should see cause, without consent of Parliament, whence it is inferred, That the King by vertue of his Soveraign Power, may erect Regalities within Sheriff-ships, and dispon on Sheriff-ships at his pleasure.</p>
            <p>To which it is Answered. 1. No such Act of Parliament Printed. 2. That in the same Kings Reign, in his sixth Parliament, <hi>cap.</hi> 61. The Sheriff-ships of <hi>Ross</hi> and <hi>Caithness</hi> were Erected, but by an express and publick Act of Parliament; So that it is not likely, that either K. <hi>James,</hi> or any other of our Kings allow that Power by themselves, and it may also be remembred that it was by Act of Parliament in the years 1661, or 1692, that the Shires of <hi>Ross</hi> and <hi>Inverness</hi> were divided; And also by an Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the year 1685, that the Shire of <hi>Kinross</hi> was augmented. But 3. What ever may be of these Acts, yet it is certain, that all Acts are only to be civily understood, that is, that the King may Unite, Disjoyne, or Erect by himself, where there is no Heretable Office, but where there was, or is an Heretable Office, the consent of the Sheriff, or else a Statute of Parliament is absolutely requisit. And 4. That the King doth not acclaim the absolute Power of disposing upon Heretable Sheriff-ships, is manifest by the Acts of Parliament 1633, And the Surrender that poceeded, and the care that the King took at that time, to buy in Heretable Sheriff-ships,, which had been a needless, and lost Expense, if so be the King might dispose upon Heretable Sheriff-ships at his pleasure. And therefore, since the King hath always ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged the Right of the Heretable Sheriffs, and that it could not be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from them, without a lawful Purchase, it is impossible, that the Regali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties can be Erected within their Bounds without their Consent to their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice.</p>
            <p rend="block">In respect whereof, The Regality in favours of the Laird of <hi>Grant,</hi> in sua far as the same comprehends Lands lying within the Sheriffdom of <hi>Elgin</hi> and <hi>Forrest,</hi> alias Sheriffdom of <hi>Murray,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the said <hi>Alexander Dumbar</hi> of <hi>Westfield</hi> is Heretable Sheriff ought to be Reduced, and the Laird of <hi>Grant</hi> Decerned in the Expenses su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stained by the Sheriff in maintaining his own Right, and reducing the said Regality, whereupon the Sheriff is willing to depone.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>